U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers 5088
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers
1936-1940
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. National Mediation Board
Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee
Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.)
5088
2.67 cubic feet
2.7 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Briefs and exhibits of Arbitration Board No. 254. Carriers represented by the Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, 1936-1960.
3116792
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 07, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
On March 5, 1960 the Carriers and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers signed an Arbitration Agreement to submit a controversy over wages to a six man arbitration board consisting of Archibald Cox, Richard A. Lester, Roy E. Davidson, D. S. Beattle, G. W. Knight, and J. E. Wolfe. The agreement specified the following questions were all that the Board was to decide.
1. Shall all or any part of the request of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, dated March 2, 1959 be granted?
2. Shall all or any part of the proposal of the carriers served on or about March 20, 1959 be granted?
The termination of the national wage agreement signed in 1957 prompted the Engineers to request a 12 per cent increase in basic daily rates for locomotive engineers together with arbitraries, miscellaneous rates, etc., and the incorporation into the basic rates of the accumulated cost-of living allowances. The carriers countered with a proposal for a 15 cent across the board wage reduction and elimination of the cost of living escalation clause.
Unable to reach an agreement, the National Mediation Board was appealed to on September 24, 1959 under the procedures of the Railway Labor Act. Mediation was not successful, but the National Mediation Board persuaded the parties to submit the wage issue to binding arbitration. All other issues were referred to the Presidential Study Commission.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5081: U.S. National Mediation Board United Air Lines Findings 5082: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcript of Hearings Regarding the BRAC 5083: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding United Air Lines and Air Line Pilots Association 5085: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding American Air Lines and Transport Workers Union of America 5086: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding New York Central Railroad Company and BRAC 5087: U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers 5089: U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding General Managers Association of New York and the International Longshoremen's Association, Lighter Captains Union, Local 996 5090: U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Chicago and Northwestern Railway Company et al. and the Order of Railroad Telegraphers 5579: National Mediation Board Emergency Board 180, Train Crew Consists 5748 OHM: National Mediation Board Airline Industry Arbitration Oral History Interviews 5806: U.S. National Mediation Board Agreements
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Sources; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States -- Sources; United States. National Mediation Board. Arbitration Board No. 254; United States. National Mediation Board; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.) -- Sources
3116792
- Prehearing and Post-hearing briefs for the Carriers'; Carriers' Exhibits (Box 1)
  - Prehearing and Post-hearing briefs for the Carriers'. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit A. Eastern Railroads represented by the Eastern Carriers Conference Committee. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exhibit B. Western Railroads represented by the Western Carriers Conference Committee. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibit C. Southeastern Railroads represented by the Southeastern Carriers Conference Committee. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. The Proposals of the Parties. The Appearances for the Carriers and the Arbitration Agreement. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2. Rates of pay for through Freight Engineers and Machinists. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 3. Railroad Employees and their Compensation. Relation of Labor Costs to Revenue Per Unit of Output. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 4. Job Descriptions and Illustrative Examples of Payroll Positions and Duties. Supervisory and Non-operating Employees. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 5. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 6. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 7. Inter and Intra Industry Wage and Earning Comparisons. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 8. Wage Progress of Railroad Employees and Production Workers in Manufacturing Industries. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 9. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 10. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 11. Inter Industry Wage and Earnings Comparisons. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 12. Data Supplementing Certain of the Employees' Exhibits. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 13. Safety of Railroad Operations. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 14. The Inability of the Railroads to Bear Employment Cost Increases. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 15. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 16. Relationship Between Straight Time Hourly Earnings and Pro Rate Hourly Earnings - Locomotive Engineers. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 17. Tables and Supporting Materials - Recent Wage Agreements in the Railroad Industry; Timing of Wage Adjustments; The Escalator Clause Issue. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 18. The Pennsylvania Railroad. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 19. Explanation of Provisions of Recent Wage Agreements. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 20. Employee Demands Presently Confronting the Railroad Industry and Estimated Costs Thereof. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 21. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 22. Miscellaneous Materials on Job Content. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 23. Job Content and Working Conditions of Engineers. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 24. Employee Evaluation of Employment. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 25. Employee Evaluation of Employment (Statistical Tables). (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 26. R. J. Dimmitt - Personal Experience Testimony. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 27. Transfer Run 49, Chicago and North Western Railway. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 28. Chicago, Milwaukee, Saint Paul and Pacific Railroad Seniority Rosters as of January 1, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 29. Personal Experience Job Content Testimony for W.D. Quarles. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 30. Productivity - A False Wage Determinant. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 31. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 32. Average Straight Time Hourly Earnings. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 33. Analysis of Increases in Straight Time Hourly Earnings Per Hour Worked of Road and Yard Engineers - 1936 to Current., 1936-1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Scope and Contents
    1936-1960?
  - 34. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 35. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 36. Earnings, Miles and Hours of 30 Engineers Engaged Exclusively in Through Freight and Converted Through Freight Service with Highest Earnings Per Hour on Duty. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 37. Average Straight Time Hourly Earnings of Non-operating Employees and Production Workers in Manufacturing Industries. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 38. Average Straight Time Hourly Earnings of Road and Yard Engineers and Production Workers in Manufacturing Industries. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 39. Real Full-Time Weekly Earnings of Production Workers in All Manufacturing Industries., 1921-1941 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 40. Excerpts from Testimony, Exhibits and Briefs Presented by the Organizations to Emergency and Arbitration Boards Relating to the Wages of Railroad Employees. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 41. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 42. No information available. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 43. Excerpts from Productivity, Prices, and Income. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Union Exhibits; Agreement; Transcript (Box 2)
  - 1. Description of the Organization, Membership and Structure of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2. Form of Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers' Wage Request - Section 6 Notice, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    March 2, 1959.
  - 3. Letter from Mr. Robert O. Boyd, Chairman, National Mediation Board, to the parties., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    March 5, 1960.
  - 4. Letter from Mr. E.C. Thompson, Executive Secretary, National Mediation Board, to the parties., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    February 2, 1960.
  - 5. Brotherhood acceptance of the proffer of arbitration. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 6. Form of Carriers' request for wage increase - undated Section 6 Notice. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 7. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 8. Standard Basic Daily Wage Rates for Locomotive Engineers on Railroads in the United States (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Effective November 1, 1958, Including .24 Cost-of-Living Adjustments Effective November 1, 1959 - Total Cost-of-Living Allowance $1.28
  - 9. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 10. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 11. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 12. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 13. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 14. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 15. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 16. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 17. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 18. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 19. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 20. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 21. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 22. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 23. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 24. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 25. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 26. Recent changes in Labor Costs and Carrier Net Income. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 27. Classification and Number of Road and Yard Service Engineers. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 28. Cost-of-Living Clauses In Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 29. Increased Length, Weight, and Speed of Trains. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 30. Railway Traffic Service Per Employee and Per Man-Hour. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 31. Real Wages - Health, Education, and Welfare of American Workers (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 32. Changes in Wage Rates and Average Earnings of Locomotive Engineers. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 33. Wage Changes, Locomotive Engineers and other Skilled American Workers. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 34. Average Straight Time Hourly Rate and Average Straight Time Hourly Earnings - All Railway Employees, 1936-1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 35. Railroad Accidents - Responsibilities and Physical Hazards of Locomotive Engineers. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 36. Basis of Pay and Assignment of Employees. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 37. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 38. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 39. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 40. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 41. Average Straight Time Hourly Earnings of Railroad Non-operating Employees and Production Workers in Manufacturing Industries. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 42. Money and Percentage Differences Between the Straight Time Hourly Earnings of Production Workers in Manufacturing Industries and 95 Classes of Railroad Operating and Non-Operating Employees. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 43. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 44. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 45. Railroad Accidents. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 46. No information available. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 47. Regulations and Earnings in Incentive Wage Systems. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 48. Base Dates for Wage Comparisons and Recent Employment Trends. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 49. Railway Financial Position. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - 50. The Railroad Industry - Investors' Earnings, Yields, and Outlook. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Agreement Between Railroads Represented by the Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and Engineers (Motormen) of Such Carriers Represented by the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    June 6, 1960.
  - Transcript of Proceedings. 22 Volumes, 2091 Pages. (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Carriers' Exhibits (Box 3)